This is the data scientist version of the zero-shot coastal bacteria result.
It walks through the panel contract, PI feature engine, model protocol, nulls, gates
washouts, and limitations.
The research question was narrow: can a label-free model train on non-target basins and rank enterococcus exceedance in a completely held-out basin
with zero target-domain labels or lab-history features as inputs?
The final scored panel had twelve domains, 708,337 held-out rows, and 57,628 events.
Rows needed a date, site, basin, coordinates, a comparable daily bacteria label
and finite PI features.
Data quality was enforced by exclusion, not wishful imputation.
Empty Wales, annual-only EEA bathing class data, pre-2012 Montenegro
and Hong Kong without coordinates were excluded from daily PI transfer.
The anti-leak feature contract allowed weather, PI groups, calendar
optional geography, and optional strings for non-headline arms.
It blocked FIB concentration, hazard labels, exceedance labels, lab-history lags
and target-domain labels.
The headline feature set was five PI groups: Damkohler-style decay, loading, UV dose
Peclet-style transport, and flushing.
These are shared physical coordinates rather than basin identity features.
We also engineered compact label-free physics kernels from the same inputs: decay-adjusted load
solar survival load, runoff memory, first flush, flushing inverse
spring-neap exchange, transport retention, and wind resuspension.
The model zoo compared calendar, PI, PI plus calendar, raw physics
physics plus geography, physics-kernel variants, and sampled CARTE strings.
The frozen public winner was PI plus logistic.
The validation split was leave-one-basin-out.
For each target, the model trained only on rows from the other basins
then scored the hidden basin.
This repeated across all twelve domains.
The primary metric was average precision
because the use case is ranking early sampling attention.
The base-rate baseline is the held-out event rate; lift is AP divided by that base rate.
The null check was source-stratum permutation.
Outcomes were shuffled within source buckets, preserving source mix
and the real AP had to beat the ninety-fifth percentile shuffled score.
It did on all twelve targets.
The freeze gate required every target above base rate
at least eighty percent above the permutation null
at least one hundred null draws per target
AP-minus-base bootstrap lower bound above zero, and mean-lift lower bound above one.
The headline PI plus logistic result was mean AP 0.1511 versus mean base rate 0.0909
for mean lift 1.752.
The domain-bootstrap AP-minus-base interval was 0.0365 to 0.086.
Per-target results were not one lucky basin.
All twelve held-out domains beat their own base rate.
The strongest lifts were Australia New South Wales, California, Ireland
and Texas; the weakest lift was North Carolina at 1.186.
The richer physics-kernel arms looked tempting on mean AP
but they washed under the promotion rule.
The best kernel added 0.0083 mean AP
but its paired-domain interval crossed zero and five targets regressed.
CARTE and entity-string variants were not frozen.
Prior same-sample fair-baseline checks failed, and full-panel CARTE was too slow
so strings did not become part of the claim.
The limitations matter.
This is a retrospective zero-shot ranking screen
not a calibrated advisory probability.
Persistence and seasonal-naive were not run because target-domain history is forbidden in the cold-start setting.
The reproducibility artifacts are the runner, markdown and JSON outputs
freeze manifest, and test file.
The caveat is that byte-reproduction from a clean clone is not yet proven because cached panels are not public frozen inputs.
The defensible data-science claim is narrow: a simple PI plus logistic ranker clears a hardened zero-shot screen for prioritizing early sampling in unseen coastal bacteria basins.